Guide to the Chester B. Himes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Chester Himes papers
1936-1980
JWJ MSS 42
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.83
(28 boxes)
The Chester Himes Papers consist of original manuscripts, correspondence, photographs and artwork that document his long career as a writer. The manuscripts offer insight into Himes's creative process and many of them also represent the original versions and original titles for works that were later altered for publication. The bulk of the correspondence reveals Himes's relationship with the publishers and editors of his books and also offers a glimpse into the author's thoughts on his own work. The photographs and artwork document Himes's life with his family, friends and colleagues.
Himes, Chester B., 1909-1984
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the author, 1953-1976. Gift of the author through Carl Van Vechten, G. P. Putnam's Sons, Doubleday and Book of the Month Club, 1952-1972. Gift of Lesley Himes, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Chester B. Himes (1909-1984)
Chester Bomar Himes was born in Jefferson City, Missouri on July 29, 1909 to Estelle Bomar Himes and Joseph Sandy Himes. He had two brothers, Edward and Joseph. Throughout his adolescent years Himes lived in Missouri, Arkansas, Georgia, Mississippi and Ohio, mainly because his father, Joseph, was a teacher who worked in these locations. Himes graduated from East High School in Cleveland, Ohio in 1926 and spent the early part of his adult life in Cleveland and Columbus, where he enrolled at Ohio State University to study medicine. He was expelled from Ohio State University in 1928 and shortly afterward was arrested, convicted for armed robbery, and sentenced, at the age of nineteen, to a twenty-five year term in prison. Himes served only part of that sentence, from 1928 to1936, at the Ohio State Penetentiary in Columbus, during which time he became a published and somewhat well-known writer. Evidently inspired to begin writing by a 1930 prison fire in which 300 inmates were killed, while in prison he published a number of articles and short stories in newspapers and magazines, most notably in Esquire.
Released from prison in 1936, he married Jean Lucinda Johnson in 1937. From 1938 to 1941 he worked for the Cleveland Daily News and the Ohio Writers' Project, for which he wrote a history of Cleveland for the WPA Guide Series. Himes moved to California in 1941 and continued writing and working at shipyards until 1944, all the while trying with little success to secure a publisher for his novel Black Sheep (later published, in 1952, as Cast the First Stone ). With the help of a Rosenwald Fellowship he was able to complete his first book, If He Hollers Let Him Go, which was published in 1945. His second book, Lonely Crusade, was published in 1947. Himes moved to Paris around 1953, and in 1955 published The Primitive. The first book of his now famous hard-boiled detective fiction series, For Love of Imabelle, which features two African American detectives from Harlem, Coffin Ed Johnson and Grave Digger Jones, was released in 1957. Himes spent the rest of his days living and writing in Europe, including stints in France, Germany and England, but primarily in Moraira on the southern coast of Spain with his second wife, Lesley Packard Himes. He published many other works including his two volume autobiography, The Quality of Hurt (1973) and My Life of Absurdity (1976). He died in Moraira, Spain on November 12, 1984.
Scope and Contents
The Chester Himes Papers consists of original manuscripts, correspondence, photographs and artwork that document his long career as a writer. The manuscripts offer insight into Himes's creative process and many of them also represent the original versions and original titles for works which were later altered for publication. The bulk of the correspondence reveals Himes's relationship with the publishers and editors of his books and also offers a glimpse into the author's thoughts on his own work. The photographs and artwork document Himes's life with his family, friends and colleagues.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Writings, 1936-1976. II. Correspondence, 1947-1980. III. Printed Material, 1947-1964. IV. Photographs and Artwork, 1953-1967. V. Estelle B. Himes Writings, undated.
African American authors; Authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographs; Drawings (visual works); Himes, Chester B., 1909-1984 -- Archives; Himes, Estelle Bomar; Targ, William, 1907-; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
- Writings, Series I; 9.34; (25 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by title of work.
  Scope and Contents
  The series is comprised of Chester Himes's original manuscript drafts, draft fragments, and miscelleaneous notes and sketches. Some of the manuscripts and draft fragments are signed by Himes and also contain handwritten corrections. The manuscripts in this series also include the original titles that Himes had for his books. The series includes galley proofs and page proofs, some with corrections and notes from Himes and the various publishers of his books.
  Some notable manuscripts in this series include, If He Hollers Let Him Go, Himes's first novel published in 1945; Lonely Crusade, his second novel, published in 1947; and Cast The First Stone, published in 1953. Also present in this series are some of Himes's short pieces of writing including an autobiographical essay and an essay on his impressions of life in Europe.
  - All Shot up
    General note
    Author's original title: Don't Play with Death
    - Setting typescript (original), signed, 1959 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
      With author's ms. corrections and publisher's editorial markings. As published: New York, Avon Book Div., Hearst Corp. [1960].
  - Autobiographical Account, 1962 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Typescript (carbon). Autobiographical sketch written as a letter to John Williams. With additional typed and autograph notes on his family history, 2 leaves. See also William's interview with Himes published in Amistad I, 1970, p. 25-93.
  - Autobiographical Sketch, 1964 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Big Gold Dream
    - Setting typescript (original), 1958 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
      With ms. corrections and publisher's editorial markings. As published: New York, Avon Book Div., Hearst Corp. [1960].
  - Blind Man with a Pistol
    - Typescript (original), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
      Leaves 273-289 are xeroxes. With clipping mounted on second leaf.
    - Another typescript (carbon), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16-20)
      Corrected version, with the author's ms. corrections.
    - Photographic copy of above: pp. 1-[305], 1969 (Box 2, Folder 21-26)
      With ms. editorial markings.
    - Galley Proofs, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 260)
      With the author's ms. corrections and editorial markings.
    - Page Proofs, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 261)
  - A Case of Rape
    - Typescript (carbon), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
      Published in French, with title, Une Affaire de Viol (1963)
  - Cast the First Stone
    Author's original titles: Black Sheep and Yesterday Will Make You Cry.
    - Notes and References, typescript (original) and author's ms. (original), 1936-1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Includes signed pencil sketch by Himes of a prison courtyard, entitled "Journey's End," and letter from "Prince Rico" to Himes.
    - Black Sheep, typescript (original), 1952 (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
      Incomplete, discarded leaves only? With the author's ms. corrections. Including a list of ten suggested titles.
    - Yesterday Will Make You Cry, typescript (original), signed, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 33-38)
      Original version of his novel Cast the First Stone. With 2 additional leaves laid in.
    - Setting typescript (original), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 39-45)
      With author's corrections, revisions and editorial markings. A novel; published; New York, Coward-McCann, inc. 1952.
  - Cotton Comes to Harlem
    - Agreement between Chester Himes and G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1964 June 5 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Setting typescript (original), signed, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 47-50)
      With ms. corrections and editorial markings.
    - Galley Proofs, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 262)
    - Galley Proofs, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 263)
      Another set: As published: New York, G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1965.
    - Page Proof, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 264)
  - The Crazy Kill
    Author's original title: A Jealous Man Can't Win
    - Typescript (original), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 51-53)
      With author's ms. corrections and publisher's editorial markings. Published: New York, Avon Book Div., Hearst Corp. 1959.
    - Xerox copy of above, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 54-57)
      Setting copy, with additional ms. corrections and editorial markings.
  - Day after Day
    - Typescript (original), signed, undated (Box 6, Folder 58-62)
      With author's ms. corrections.
  - For Love of Imabelle
    Author's original title: The Five Cornered Square.
    - Setting typescript (original), undated (Box 6, Folder 63-66)
      With author's ms. corrections and publisher's editorial markings.
      Published in France as La reine des pommes (1958)
  - The Heat's On
    - Setting typescript (original), 1966 (Box 6, Folder 67-70)
      Author's ms. corrections and misc. editorial markings.
    - Galley Proofs, 1965 September 28 (Box 25, Folder 265)
      With a few author's corrections including editorial markings.
  - If He Hollers Let Him Go
    Authors original title: Breakout
    - Synopsis of a novel, signed, undated (Box 7, Folder 71)
      With inscription by author.
    - Typescript (original), signed, 1947 February 5 (Box 7, Folder 72-75)
      With author's corrections and inscription.
    - Typescript (carbon), signed, 1947 February 5 (Box 7, Folder 76-81)
      With author's inscription.
  - Impressions of Europe, 1954 March 1 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    Typescript (carbon), signed. An account of his experiences in England, France and Spain. Dated 1 March 1954, Mallorca, Spain. Submitted to Ebony.
  - The Job of Writing, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Lonely Crusade
    - Draft fragments, undated (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - "The Anatomy of Fear", undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - "First Idea", undated (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - "Fear", undated (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - "The Magnificent Inspiration", undated (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Chapter Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - The Coleman Case Transcript, undated (Box 8, Folder 91)
      With the author's ms. corrections. Excerpts from the criminal case against Festus Coleman quoted extensively in chapter 9 of his novel, Lonely Crusade.
    - "The Orbit of Obsession", undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - Typescript (original), 1947 March 8 (Box 8, Folder 93-102)
    - Typescript (original), 1947 March 8 (Box 9, Folder 103-110)
    - Typescript (carbon), 1947 March 8 (Box 9, Folder 111-115)
    - Typescript (carbon), 1947 March 8 (Box 10, Folder 116-119)
    - Setting typescript, 1947 April 2 (Box 10, Folder 120-128)
      With author's ms. corrections
    - Galley proofs, 1947 (Box 26, Folder 266-267)
  - Memo to Liberals, undated (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - My Life of Absurdity
    - Setting typescript (original), 1976 (Box 11, Folder 130-139)
      With author's ms. corrections and editorial markings.
      His autobiography Vol. II.
    - Xerox of setting typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 140-143)
    - Final galley proof, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 268)
    - Page proof, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 269)
      With a few ms. editorial markings.
  - "Now is the Time! Here is the Place!", 1942 September (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - Pinktoes
    Author's original title: Mamie Mason.
    - Typescript (original), signed, undated (Box 13, Folder 145-148)
      With the author's ms. corrections, and his subtitle, "An Exercise in Good Will".
    - Typescript (original), signed, undated (Box 13, Folder 149-153)
      With the author's ms. corrections and revisions, and his subtitle, "An Exercise in Good Will". With four additional leaves (photostats) of earlier page proof.
    - Page Proof, 1961,1965 (Box 27, Folder 270)
  - The Present Tense
    - Typescript (original; inc.), undated (Box 14, Folder 154-162)
      With author's extensive ms. corrections and additions sometimes on the versos of leaves.
  - The Primitive
    Author's original title: The End of a Primitive.
    - Typescript (original), 1954 June 21 (Box 15, Folder 163-166)
      A novel. Published: New York, New American Library [1956]. With a TLS from Himes to William Targ. World Publishing C0., 1954 Jun. 21, Mallorca, SP.
    - Typescript (carbon), 1953 (Box 15, Folder 167-168)
      Revised version.
  - The Quality of Hurt: The Autobiography of Chester Himes
    - Setting typescript (original), 1972 (Box 16, Folder 169-177)
      With the author's ms. corrections and editorial markings. His autobiography, Volume I.
    - Another setting typescript (xerox copy), 1972 (Box 17, Folder 178-184)
      Final version, with ms. corrections and editorial markings.
    - Galley Proofs, 1972 (Box 27, Folder 271)
  - The Real Cool Killers
    Author's original title: If Trouble was Money.
    - Typescript (carbon), signed, undated (Box 18, Folder 185-187)
      With the author's ms. corrections, revisions and a few editorial markings. Published: New York, Avon Book Div., Hearst Corp. [1959].
    - Typescript (carbon), undated (Box 18, Folder 188-190)
      Earlier version, with a few author's ms. corrections.
  - The Silver Altar
    - Typescript (original), signed, undated (Box 19, Folder 191-199)
      Draft, with author's extensive ms. corrections and revisions. Written in collaboration with Willa Thompson.
  - Statement of a Plan of Work, 1947 January 17 (Box 19, Folder 200)
    Typescript (carbon). Submitted with an application to the Rosenwald Foundation.
  - Stool Pigeon, 1947 May 12 (Box 19, Folder 201)
    Typescript (carbon). Draft of a synopsis for a story about a prison fire.
  - The Third Generation
    Author's original titles: Three Generations and The Cord.
    - Notes, typescripts and autograph mss, undated (Box 20, Folder 202-204)
      Includes identifications of characters, plot outline, synopsis of the ending. Also includes miscelleaneous fragments and drafts.
    - Prologue, typescript (original), undated (Box 20, Folder 205-206)
      Drafts of episodes probably intended as an introduction to his The Third Generation, relating to the Manning family history. With author's extensive ms. corrections and revisions. Including a corrected version of the prologue for the title The Cord and an original prologue with corrections for the title Three Generations.
    - Three Generations, prologue, another typescript (original), undated (Box 20, Folder 207)
      A revised draft of the above version. Incomplete, with the author's ms. corrections and additions. Using the subtitle: Book I...The First Generation.
    - Early draft, typescript (original) and autograph ms., undated (Box 20, Folder 208)
      Preliminary working versions, with extensive corrections and typed revisions pasted in. Incomplete, with drafts of chapters, I, II and portions of III-V only.
    - Another early draft, typescript (original), undated (Box 20, Folder 209)
      Draft with author's extensive ms. corrections and revisions, sometimes on versos of leaves. Incomplete.
    - Another early draft, typescript (original), undated (Box 20, Folder 210)
      Later draft incorporating revisions of above draft with additional ms. corrections. Incomplete.
    - The Cord, incomplete drafts, autograph ms., undated (Box 20, Folder 211)
      Working draft, incomplete, of chapters I, II and III with many typed revisions pasted in.
    - The Cord, incomplete draft, typescript (original), undated (Box 20, Folder 212)
      Draft, incomplete, with author's extensive corrections and revisions, sometimes on versos of leaves.
    - The Cord, typescript (original), 1954 (Box 21, Folder 213-217)
      Later draft with extensive ms. corrections, revisions and some editorial markings.Leaves 10, 13-27, 316 lacking.
    - The Cord, another typescript (original), undated (Box 21, Folder 218-219)
      Drafts and miscellaneous fragments deleted from the above version.
    - The Cord, final draft, another typescript (original), undated (Box 22, Folder 220-224)
      With author's ms. corrections and some editorial markings.
  - Unidentified writings, draft fragments, undated (Box 22, Folder 225)
- Correspondence, Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series II. is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  The series contains a small amount of Himes's incoming and outgoing correspondence. The bulk of the correspondence documents Himes's professional relationships with G.P. Putnam's Sons editor William Targ and photographer and writer Carl Van Vechten. The letters between Targ and Himes date from when Targ served as editor and editor in chief at two different publishing companies, The World Publishing Company, where he was from 1942 until 1964, and G. P. Putnam's Sons, where he worked from 1964 until 1978. The series also includes one letter from Himes to Helen Meyer, editor at Dell Publishing Co. Inc and four letters from Himes to Roslyn Targ, wife of William Targ and owner of Roslyn Targ Literary Agency Inc.
  A large amount of the correspondence discusses contracts and payments for some of Himes's manuscripts and movie contracts. Some of the letters contain considerable discussion about discrepancies in payments and contracts for Himes's book, Cotton Comes To Harlem, which was turned into a movie. Other letters discuss Himes's life traveling in Europe and his life in Spain. The letters also discuss Himes's disapproval of the way publishers edited some of his books. In a letter to Helen Meyer, Himes protests the cover and descriptive copy of his book Run Man Run. Carl Van Vechten's letters discuss Himes's writings, his gifts to Yale, his travels, and their mutual friends and interests.
  - Meyer, Helen, 1969 January 31 (Box 22, Folder 226)
  - "Prince Rico"
    See: Series I. Writings, Cast the First Stone.
  - Roslyn Targ Literary Agency Inc., 1972-1976 (Box 22, Folder 227)
  - Targ, William, 1948-1980, undated (Box 22, Folder 228-240)
    Includes a letter from Samuel Goldwyn, Jr., to Himes, a letter from from Targ to Goldwyn, and a letter from Anthony Boucher to Targ.
  - Van Vechten, Carl
    - 1947-1957 (Box 22, Folder 241)
    - 1958-1964 (Box 22, Folder 241a)
- Printed Material, Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  The bulk of this series consists of clippings of reviews of Himes's second novel, Lonely Crusade. Although sales of the book in the United States did not reflect this, when Lonely Crusade was first released it caused a considerable amount of controversy. As a result, a large number of book reviews were published in major newspapers such as The New Yorker, The New York Times, The Cleveland Plain Dealer and The New York Post as well as in smaller African American newspapers and magazines such as The Chicago Defender and The Crisis. The series also includes reviews by major figures in the literary and journalism world during the mid-twentieth century including Arna Bontemps, James Baldwin, Guy Savino, William Targ and Willard Motley. Some of the clippings also discuss Himes's life, his work and his travels in Europe.
  - Reviews: Lonely Crusade, 1947-1948 (Box 23, Folder 242-244)
  - Oversize reviews: Lonely Crusade, 1947 (Box 28, Folder 245)
  - Other clippings and photocopies, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 246)
- Photographs and Artwork, Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  The photographs in this series document Himes's life with his family and friends. The series includes portraits of Himes, reproductions of snapshots of Himes as a child and as a teenager and also some photographs of his mother, Estelle Bomar Himes, and his brother Joseph S. Himes, Jr.. Also included in this series are photographs of Himes with Regine Fischer, and a number of images of Himes in the studio and home of his friend Walter Coleman, the American painter. Coleman's wife was the silversmith Torun Bülow-Hübe, and there are several photographs of her and her work. Also included are two photographs of Himes speaking on a panel that includes Rebecca West at an event in France celebrating the thirtieth anniversary of Feux Croisés, and two photographs of Himes with French author Jean Giono.
  Dates pencilled on the photographs were added by the library at the time of acquisition, and refer to letters from Himes to Carl Van Vechten, which can be found in the Carl Van Vechten Papers. These letters provide context for the photographs.
  - Portraits of Chester Himes, 1957,1963, undated (Box 23, Folder 247)
  - Himes Family, 1957,1959 (Box 23, Folder 248)
  - Himes with Regine Fischer, 1957-1959 (Box 23, Folder 249)
  - Himes with Jean Giono, 1957-1959 (Box 23, Folder 250)
  - Himes and Lesley Packard with Walter Coleman and Torun Bülow-Hübe, 1960 Dec 25 (Box 23, Folder 251)
  - Feux Croisés celebration, 1957 May 21 (Box 23, Folder 252-253)
    Includes images of Gabriel Marcel, Himes, Rebecca West, Maurice Bourdel, Rosalina Coelho Lisboa, Nikos Kazantzaki, Jose-Maria Gironella, Max-Pol Fouchet.
    Accompanied by event program and booklet, Feux Croisés: Ames et Terres Etrangeres (Numéro Spécial du Lisez-Plon, Nouvelle Série 1/1957).
  - Postcards of Arachon, France, 1953 (Box 23, Folder 254)
  - Christmas card to William and Roslyn Targ, collage by Lesley Himes, 1967 December (Box 28, Folder 255)
  - Original drawing, untitled, anonymous, undated (Box 28, Folder 256)
  - "Journey's End," pencil sketch of prison yard
    See: Series I. Writings, Cast the First Stone
- Estelle B. Himes Writings, Undated; Series V; 3
  - Notes on the Himes family history, autograph ms. and typescript, Undated (Box 23, Folder 257)
  - "The Ol' Lick Log," draft (incomplete) of a novel, autograph ms., Undated (Box 23, Folder 258)
  - Poems, autograph ms. and typescripts, Undated (Box 23, Folder 259)
    Contents: 1. Autumn, 2. The Commission, 3. The Graduate, 4. My Business School Teacher, 5. The Party, 6. A La-Invicuts, 7. The Storm.